<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://doriangailhard.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://doriangailhard.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-09-23T13:41:33+00:00</updated><id>https://doriangailhard.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>My personal webpage. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">HYGENE: A Diffusion-based Hypergraph Generation Method</title><link href="https://doriangailhard.github.io/blog/2024/HYGENE/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="HYGENE: A Diffusion-based Hypergraph Generation Method"/><published>2024-08-23T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://doriangailhard.github.io/blog/2024/HYGENE</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://doriangailhard.github.io/blog/2024/HYGENE/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="hygene-a-diffusion-based-hypergraph-generation-method">HYGENE: A Diffusion-based Hypergraph Generation Method</h1> <p>In the ever-evolving landscape of machine learning and graph theory, we’re excited to introduce HYGENE (HYpergraph GENEration), a groundbreaking approach to generating hypergraphs using diffusion-based methods. This blog post outlines our research, methodology, and key findings presented at a recent conference.</p> <h2 id="introduction-to-hypergraphs">Introduction to Hypergraphs</h2> <p>Before diving into our method, let’s briefly review what hypergraphs are and why they’re important.</p> <p><img src="assets/img/graph_vs_hypergraph.png" alt="Graph vs Hypergraph"/></p> <p>While traditional graphs consist of nodes connected by edges, hypergraphs take this concept a step further. In a hypergraph, edges (called hyperedges) can connect any number of nodes, allowing for the representation of more complex and higher-order relationships.</p> <p>This enhanced flexibility makes hypergraphs ideal for modeling a wide range of systems and phenomena, including:</p> <ol> <li>3D Meshes: Where hyperedges represent triangles or other polygons.</li> <li>Electronic Circuits: Grouping components connected to the same router.</li> <li>Pharmaceutical Research: Representing atomic structures and compound relationships.</li> </ol> <h2 id="the-challenge-hypergraph-generation">The Challenge: Hypergraph Generation</h2> <p>Despite their utility, the field of hypergraph generation has been largely unexplored, especially in the context of deep learning. Our research aims to fill this gap by developing a method capable of generating hypergraphs that preserve the essential properties of a given “class” or dataset.</p> <h2 id="our-approach-multi-resolution-generation">Our Approach: Multi-Resolution Generation</h2> <p>Inspired by recent advancements in graph generation, we adopted a multi-resolution approach for HYGENE. This method avoids the ordering problems associated with spatial generation techniques and allows for a more natural and controlled generation process.</p> <p><img src="assets/img/multi_resolution_generation.png" alt="Multi-Resolution Generation"/></p> <p>Our process involves:</p> <ol> <li>Creating a “coarsening” sequence from input hypergraphs</li> <li>Training models to invert this coarsening process</li> <li>Generating new hypergraphs by iteratively applying these models</li> </ol> <h2 id="technical-innovation-dual-representation">Technical Innovation: Dual Representation</h2> <p>A key innovation in our approach is the use of dual representations for hypergraphs:</p> <ol> <li>Weighted Clique Expansion: Used for the coarsening process</li> <li>Bipartite View: Employed for the generation phase</li> </ol> <p><img src="assets/img/hypergraph_projections.png" alt="Hypergraph Projections"/></p> <p>This dual representation allows us to leverage existing graph coarsening techniques while maintaining the ability to easily reconstruct hypergraphs during generation.</p> <h2 id="the-hygene-pipeline">The HYGENE Pipeline</h2> <p>Our method follows these main steps:</p> <ol> <li>Coarsen input hypergraphs using weighted clique expansion</li> <li>Maintain a parallel bipartite view of the hypergraph</li> <li>Train models to reconstruct the bipartite graph</li> <li>Generate new hypergraphs by iteratively applying the trained models</li> </ol> <p><img src="assets/img/hygene_pipeline.png" alt="HYGENE Pipeline"/></p> <h2 id="results-and-evaluation">Results and Evaluation</h2> <p>We evaluated HYGENE on a variety of datasets, including synthetic hypergraphs and real-world data from 3D mesh topologies. Our results demonstrate that HYGENE can effectively capture and reproduce various hypergraph properties across different domains.</p> <p>Here are some examples of generated hypergraphs compared to the training samples:</p> <p><img src="assets/img/erdos_renyi_results.png" alt="Erdos-Renyi Results"/> <em>Erdos-Renyi Hypergraphs: Training samples (left) vs. Generated samples (right)</em></p> <p><img src="assets/img/sbm_results.png" alt="Stochastic Block Model Results"/> <em>Stochastic Block Model Hypergraphs: Training samples (left) vs. Generated samples (right)</em></p> <p><img src="assets/img/mesh_results.png" alt="3D Mesh Results"/> <em>3D Mesh Topology (Piano): Training samples (left) vs. Generated samples (right)</em></p> <h2 id="conclusion-and-future-work">Conclusion and Future Work</h2> <p>HYGENE represents a significant step forward in the field of hypergraph generation. By leveraging diffusion-based methods and a novel dual representation approach, we’ve demonstrated the ability to generate diverse and realistic hypergraphs across various domains.</p> <p>Future work will focus on extending HYGENE to handle attributed hypergraphs and exploring its applications in areas such as drug discovery, social network analysis, and 3D graphics generation.</p> <p>We’re excited about the potential impact of this research and look forward to seeing how HYGENE can be applied to solve real-world problems and advance our understanding of complex systems.</p> <p>Stay tuned for more updates and feel free to reach out if you’re interested in collaborating or learning more about our work!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="papers"/><category term="machine-learning"/><category term="generative-models"/><category term="graph-theory"/><category term="hypergraphs"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[HYGENE]]></summary></entry></feed>